Guide to the Cedric J. Robinson and Elizabeth P. Robinson Collection on Third World News Review TAM.835
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Cedric J. Robinson and Elizabeth P. Robinson Collection on Third World News Review
1981-2015
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Robinson, Cedric J.
Robinson, Elizabeth P.
Robinson-Mayer, Najda
TAM.835
6.44 Linear Feet in 4 manuscript boxes, a half manuscript box, and 8 media boxes
1.79 Terabytes in 517 computer files
3 U-matic
15 VHS
29 audiocassettes
The Third World News Review (TWNR) was a community-led news program based at the University of California, Santa Barbara that provided a counter-narrative news source aimed at destabilizing the ways in which mainstream media outlets report on politics and foreign policy in the so-called Third World. TWNR was conceived by Cedric Robinson, Corey Dubin, and Gerard Pigeon; and was produced by Elizabeth Robinson and Beth Anderson. The Cedric J. Robinson and Elizabeth P. Robinson Collection on Third World News Review (dated 1981-2015) consists of materials documenting the creation, production, and distribution of TWNR. Materials include scripts and notes for episodes, as well as research materials mainly consisting of news articles from other media sources. The majority of the collection consists of recordings of full episodes originally recorded in analog and electronic formats, including audiocassettes, VHS tapes, U-Matic tapes, and digital files on optical discs.
Scope and Contents
The Cedric J. Robinson and Elizabeth P. Robinson Collection on Third World News Review (dated 1981-2015) consists of materials documenting the creation, production, and distribution of Third World News Review. The majority of the collection consists of recordings of full episodes on analog and electronic formats, including audiocassette, VHS, U-Matic, and optical disc. Both the productions files and episodes document the types of news stories discussed on TWNR, including political unrest and government corruption in Africa; military conflicts including the Gulf War, the Iraq War, the Lebanese Civil War, and the War in Afghanistan; American international and domestic politics; U.S. intervention overseas, particularly in Africa and the Middle East; human rights violations in Latin America, the Middle East, and Africa; riots and bombings in Europe, Southeast Asia, the Middle East, and Africa; and Western colonialism in continents like Africa and Southeast Asia.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series:
Series I: Production Files
Series II: Third World News Review (TWNR) Episodes
Materials in Series I are arranged into scripts and research materials. Episodes in Series II are arranged in chronological order by episode air date.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Elizabeth Robinson and Najda Robinson-Mayer in June 2024; the accession number associated with this gift is 2024.031.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Related Materials
The Cedric J. Robinson and Elizabeth P. Robinson Archive, consisting of the Robinsons' research and teaching papers, ephemera, and other materials related to the careers of the Robinsons, was donated to the University of California Santa Barbara by Elizabeth P. Robinson and Najda Robinson-Mayer in March 2024.
Biographical Note on Cedric Robinson
Cedric Robinson (1940-2016) was a radical and a cross-disciplinary theorist; a political scientist; a scholar of media and film studies; a co-creator and producer of multiple long-standing left community media outlets; an educator and professor; and an activist and organizer dedicated to international solidarity movements. At the University of California, Santa Barbara, he became the director of the Center for Black Studies Research. He was the author of multiple texts including, but not limited to: The Terms of Order: Political Science and the Myth of Leadership, (1980, republished in 2016); Black Marxism: The Making of the Black Radical Tradition, (1983, republished in 2000 and 2020); Black Movements in America (1997); and Forgeries of Memory and Meaning: Blacks and the Regimes of Race in American Theater and Film Before World War II (2007). He is well-known for theorizing the framework of racial capitalism.
Custodial History
This collection represents one portion of the whole of the Cedric J. Robinson and Elizabeth P. Robinson Papers, the bulk of which is held by University of California, Santa Barbara and the connections between which are guided by a cross-institutional Memorandum of Understanding between UCSB and NYU. This letter of agreement states the Cedric J. Robinson and Elizabeth P. Robinson Collection on Third World News Review and to be held at the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives.
Biographical Note on Elizabeth Robinson
Elizabeth Robinson is an educator and social worker; a community media-producer and former associate director for media at KCSB Radio; an organizer and activist; and the long-time host of No Alibis, a radical news outlet that provides commentary, from a left and community-based perspective, on local, national, and international stories.
Historical Note on Third World News Review
Along with University of California, Santa Barbara student Corey Dubin, Cedric Robinson created Third World News Review (TWNR), a long-standing community-led radio show on KCSB 91.9 FM that provided a counter-narrative news source aimed at destabilizing the ways in which mainstream media outlets report on politics and foreign policy in the so-called Third World. Though TWNR was initiated by Cedric Robinson, Corey Dubin, and Gerard Pigeon, the show must be more fully understood as having been produced collectively. Elizabeth Robinson, alongside Beth Anderson, was TWNR's co-producer in both its radio and television program formats. The show invited a wide range of scholarly and activist dialogue, with numerous correspondents and guests over the life of TWNR.
Third World News Review first aired in 1979 in the wake of what was known in Western media circles as the Iranian Hostage Crisis. Recognizing a general lack of understanding and awareness of international politics beyond the framing of U.S. imperialism amongst United States citizens, TWNR was born. The hour-long show ran weekly for 35 years and covered a range of subjects including the "Dirty War" in Argentina; the U.S. invasions of numerous Latin American countries; the Iraq War; the first and second intifadas in Palestine; the independence of Zimbabwe; and U.S. manipulation of elections in the Philippines, El Salvador, Afghanistan, and Venezuela. At every point in its three decades of production, TWNR supported global liberation movements — in particular, those in Africa, Latin America, and the Middle East. TWNR aired its last episode on October 26, 2015.
Radio programs.; Community radio; Radio broadcasters; Alternative radio broadcasting.; Alternative mass media.; Public-access television.; National liberation movements; Anti-imperialist movements.; Third world; Radio scripts.; Iraq War, 2003-2011; Audiovisual materials.; Latin America.; Middle East.; Asia.; Africa; Europe; Human rights.; Santa Barbara (Calif.); World politics.; Civil War; Persian Gulf War, 1991.; Political corruption.; United States -- Politics and government; Southeast Asia; Robinson, Elizabeth P.; Robinson-Mayer, Najda; KCSB (Radio station: Santa Barbara, Calif.)
- Series I: Production Files, 1983-2015; 1.1 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes and a half manuscript box; 194 kilobytes in 21 computer files
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains typed scripts, some of which have margin annotations, and research materials mainly consisting of news articles from other media sources, some of which have margin annotations and handwritten notes attached. Materials in this series date from 1983 to 2015 and are arranged by date ranges.
  The Third World News Review scripts focus on various topics including: the Iraq War, the Lebanese Civil War, and the Gulf War; the Iran-Contra Affair; the Palestinian Liberation Organization (PLO) and hijacking of TWA flights; Gaza, the West Bank, United States-Israeli relations, and the Pollard Affair; the United Nations conference seeking international ban on chemical weapons; the assassination of Fatah founder Khalil Ibrahim al-Wazir; the Arab League Summit; growing Contra activity and violence in Central American countries like El Salvador, Panama, and Nicaragua; growing political instability and coups in the Sudan; the 1984 anti-Sikh riots in India; the bombing at West Berlin nightclub La Belle; and critiques of the Reagan administration.
  Research materials focus on topics including tensions between the United Nations and African countries related to the attempted prosecution of corrupt government officials in countries including Uganda, Kenya, Liberia, South Africa, and Nigeria; U.S. military intervention in Somalia; economic unrest related to mines in South Africa; conflicts involving Boko Haram; protests in Egypt related to the Muslim Brotherhood; growing Islamist insurgency in Mali; Gaza; Simon Mann's trial in Equatorial Guinea; Israel and Palestine; the Rwandan genocide; U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE); investigations related to U.K. Prime Minister Tony Blair and the Iraq War; President Barack Obama and the 2012 Presidential Election; British colonialism in Africa, including the Mau Mau massacre; and the War in Afghanistan.
  - Scripts, 1983-1991
    - Paper, 1983-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - Paper, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - Paper, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - Paper, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Electronic Records, 1989-1990; TW_TAM_835_ER_1
  - Research Materials, 1989-1990, 2008-2013
    - Paper, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 9, Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Paper, 2009-2015 (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
    - Paper, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    - Paper, 2011-2013 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Paper, 2012-2015 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Paper, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Electronic Records, 1989-1990; TW_TAM_835_ER_2
  - Audio Mixing Request, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series II: Third World News Review Episodes, 1981-2015; 1.67 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes and a cassette box; 1.79 Terabytes in 496 computer files; 3 U-matic; 15 VHS; 29 audiocassettes
  This series, which comprises the majority of this collection, contains 523 full length radio and television episodes of Third World News Review. These episodes include the entirety of TWNR's run, with episodes airing between 2003-2015. While most episodes are available in a digital format, analog formats including audiocassette tapes, VHS, and U-Matic tapes can also be found in this series.
  Each episode of TWNR focused on topics such as political unrest and government corruption in Africa, Latin America, Southeast Asia, and Eastern Europe; military conflicts including the Iraq War, the War in Afghanistan, civil wars in Africa, and civil wars in the Middle East; American politics and intervention overseas; human rights violations in Latin America, the Middle East, Southeast Asia, and Africa; domestic and global protests and riots; international and domestic politics; the prosecution of war criminals and corrupt politicians at the Hague; and Western colonialism on the continents of Africa and Southeast Asia.
  The majority of the episodes are moderated by Cedric J. Robinson, who specialized in topics related to Africa. On occasion, Elizabeth P. Robinson, who specialized in topics related to the Middle East, would also moderate the program, but she more often appeared as a correspondent. Recurring correspondents on TWNR include Gerard Pigeon, who provided the Francophone press' perspective on news stories; Hector Javkin, Ralph Ambruster-Sandoval, and Corey Dubin, all of whom specialized in topics related to Latin America; Gary Colmenar, who specialized in topics related to Asia and Southeast Asia; Katia McClain, who specialized in topics related to Central and Eastern Europe; Thomas Jacob, who specialized in topics related to Southeast Asia; and Ilya Ahmadizadeh who specialized in Spain, the Middle East, and occasionally discussed Latin America.
  Other correspondents on the show include Lisa Hajjar, H.L.T (HQ) Quan, Avery Gordon, Phoebe Hirsch Dubin, Will Thomas, Dadie Aime Loh, Paul Lynch, Yoel Haile, Huwe Jikata, Amr El Abbadi, Kathleen Bruhn, Christine Shearer, Alina Smiyun, Manuel Gil, Oscar Gil, Mark Schuller, Mark Manning, Jennifer Rogers, Ian Thompson, Raquel Lopez, Kevin McKiernan, Brian Brown, Enita David, Ghazala Rafiq, Ben Daouda Toure, Jovian Radheshwar, Marcus Lopez, Michael Dorsey, Lucy Edwards, Mahader Tesfai, Maryam Griffin, Daniel Alvarenga, Meriem Ouederni, Jorge Ramirez, Maryam Griffin, Jim Phillips, Peter Shapiro, Kofi Nyawuto, Jihad, Nelcya Delanoe, Sherrie Higgins, Suzanne Avellano, Philip Roettinger, David MacMichael, Daniel Ellsberg, and Louis Wolf.
  When available, episodes in digital format have been listed with a brief description providing information about the episode's moderator, correspondents, and topics discussed. For frequent correspondents, like Hector Javkin or Gerard Pigeon, their geographic specialities are noted in the series level scope and content note. For less frequent correspondents, like Lisa Hajjar or Raquel Lopez, their specialities are noted next to their names in parentheses.
  Arrangement
  Episodes in this series are arranged in chronological order by air date.
  - May 12, 1981 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0005)
  - 1982 (Box 5, Vhs 835_0030)
  - 1984, TW_TAM_835_ER_4
    This digital file contained two episodes.
    The moderator of the first episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Peter Shapiro (South Africa), Elizabeth Robinson, Kofi Nyawuto (Africa), Corey Dubin, and Jihad (Middle East). Discussed topics include a Guinean coup d'état and attempted coup d'état in Cameroon; the Nkomati Accords between South Africa and Mozambique; South African Border War/Angolan Bush War; prison reform and Apartheid in South Africa; droughts in Africa leading to widespread starvation; Nicaragua suing the U.S. in the world court for its involvement in mining ports; Nicaraguan contras and the CIA; El Salvador government forcing sterilization of women; white paper on Grenada invasion released by the U.K. government; upcoming Israeli elections; charges against Iraq for using chemical weapons; and elections in the Middle East.
    The moderator of the second episode was Elizabeth Robinson and the guests were Peter Shapiro (South Africa), Nelcya Delanoe (Nicaragua), Sherie Higgins (Nicaragua), Suzanne Avellano (Latin America), and Kofi Nyawuto (Africa). Discussed topics include Apartheid in South Africa; negotiations about the release of President Nelson Mandela; civil and political unrest in Africa; Nicaraguan contras, the Sandinista National Liberation Front, Creoles, indigenous peoples of Nicaragua, and U.S. involvement in Nicaragua; and the Union Carbide India Limited (UCIL) leak in Bhopal.
  - June 17, 1985 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0016)
  - June 25, 1985 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0016)
  - July 8, 1985 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0017)
  - July 16, 1985 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0017)
  - July 23, 1985 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0015)
  - August 20, 1985 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0020)
  - August 26, 1985 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0019)
  - September 3, 1985 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0019)
  - October 29, 1985 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0011)
  - November 4, 1985 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0011)
  - December 24, 1985 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0025)
  - April 7, 1986 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0018)
  - April 13, 1986 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0018)
  - June 23, 1986 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0023)
  - June 30, 1986 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0023)
  - January 25, 1988 (Box 5, Vhs 835_0034)
  - Circa 1980s, TW_TAM_835_ER_3
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Corey Dubin, Philip Roettinger (CIA in Central America), David MacMichael (CIA in Central America), Elizabeth Robinson, Daniel Ellsberg (State Department/Department of Defense), Louis Wolf (Editor of Covert Action Bulletin), and Jim Philips (Central America). Discussed topics include President Vinicio Cerezo of Guatemala and the current political and military situation; ARDIS (Association for Responsible Dissent); the history of U.S. involvement with coups globally; and American foreign policy and the use of the CIA to meet those goals.
  - August 1990 (Box 6, U-matic 835_0042)
  - May 20, 1991 (Box 5, Vhs 835_0032)
  - January 25, 1993 (Box 5, Vhs 835_0031)
  - February 8, 1993 (Box 5, Vhs 835_0031)
  - April 7, 1997 (Box 6, Vhs 835_0047)
  - April 10, 2000 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0024)
  - May 1, 2000 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0026)
  - May 8, 2000 (Box 5, Vhs 835_0041)
  - September 25, 2000 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0026)
  - April 8, 2001 (Box 5, Vhs 835_0033, 835_0036)
  - July 9, 2001 (Box 5, Vhs 835_0038)
  - August 6, 2001 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0002)
  - September 17, 2001
    - Audio (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0001)
    - Video (Box 5, Vhs 835_0037)
  - October 1, 2001 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0002)
  - October 15, 2001 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0001)
  - December 17, 2001 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0003)
  - Circa 2002, TW_TAM_835_ER_5
    The moderator was Elizabeth Robinson and the guests were Katia McClain and Gerard Pigeon. This was a retrospective episode looking back at some of the top news stories covered on the program. Those topics included the CIA's involvement with mining ports in Nicaragua; ARDIS (Association for Responsible Dissent); Israeli politics in 1984; the U.K. producing mustard gas for Iraq during the Iran-Iraq War; the ongoing conflict between Israel and Palestine; 9/11; and the Iraq War.
  - January 6, 2002, TW_TAM_835_ER_6
    The moderator of this episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Gerard Pigeon and Elizabeth Robinson. Topics discussed include the National Rainbow Coalition (NARC) victory in the Kenyan elections; UN intervention for ceasefire negotiation for the Ivorian Civil War; President Yasser Arafat canceling Palestinian elections; elections in Israel and growing scandals surrounding the Likud party; and the Iraq War.
  - August 5, 2002 (Box 5, Vhs 835_0039)
  - October 14, 2002 (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0006)
  - November 18, 2002
    - Audio (Box 4, Audiocassette 835_0006)
    - Video (Box 5, Vhs 835_0040)
  - December 30, 2002, TW_TAM_835_ER_7
    The moderator of this episode was Elizabeth Robinson and the guests were Hector Javkin and Katia McClain. Topics discussed include growing anti-Arabic sentiment in the United States; the Kosovo War, Albania's desire for independence, and Balkanization; an explosion in Chechnya; Venezuela beginning to import oil despite major strikes; and an attempted coup against President Hugo Chávez.
  - January 13, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_8
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Hector Javkin and Katia McClain. Discussed topics include gun law reform in the United States; the International Criminal Court and the trial of President Slobodan Milošević; the Bosnian War; the death of General Leopold Galtieria and his legacy; and demonstrations in Liberia in opposition to the United Nations sanctions against Liberia.
  - January 27, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_9
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Gerard Pigeon and Ralph Ambruster-Sandoval. Discussed topics include the Truth and Reconciliation Commissions in Sierra Leone and Burundi; the search for Major Johnny Paul Koroma; the First Ivorian Civil War and Accra II Peace Talks; the Iraq War; ongoing violence in the Gaza strip; discussion of the documentary In the Mirror of Maya Deren; the World Social Forum; and general strikes in Venezuela against President President Hugo Chávez.
  - February 3, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_10
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Elizabeth Robinson and Avery Gordon (Brazil). Discussed topics include the Duke and Duchess of Windsor (Edward VIII and Wallis Simpson) and the Nazis; the World Social Forum meeting in Brazil; the World Economic Forum in Davos; ongoing conflict in the Gaza Strip; and allegations against the United States regarding torture.
  - February 24, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_11
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Gary Colmenar and Gerard Pigeon. Discussed topics include Abu Sayyaf and Muslim extremists in the Philippines; American imperialism in the Philippines; the Taliban and the War in Afghanistan; the Iraq War; and the growing anti-war movement globally.
  - March 3, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_12
    The moderator of the episode was Elizabeth Robinson and the guest was Ralph Ambruster-Sandoval. Discussed topics include the Iraq War and a global labor press conference with international labor leaders opposing the war; the United States eavesdropping on members of the United Nations; the ongoing teacher strike in Guatemala; the upcoming midterm elections in Mexico; and increased insurgency activity in Nepal against Maoists.
  - March 10, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_13
    The moderator of the episode was Elizabeth Robinson and the guests were Katia McClain, Dadie Aime Loh (Ivory Coast), and Gerard Pigeon. Discussed topics include the United Nations investigation into the United States eavesdropping on other delegations; the Iraq War; and political instability in Ivory Coast, the history of French imperialism, and the 1999 Ivorian coup d'état.
  - March 17, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_14
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Thomas Jacob and Elizabeth Robinson. Discussed topics include the Iraq War; the Vandenberg Action Coalition; the death of Rachel Corrie in Rafah, Gaza Strip; and upcoming demonstrations in Paraguay against U.S. intervention in Iraq.
  - March 24, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_15
    The moderator of the episode was Cedric Robinson and the guests were Elizabeth Robinson and Gerard Pigeon. Discussed topics include the death of Rachel Corrie in Rafah, Gaza Strip; the Iraq War; Geneva Convention violations in Guantanamo Bay; and American interests in Iraqi oil.
  - March 31, 2003, TW_TAM_835_ER_16